A Guide to the Encampment for Citizenship Collection, 1939-1941, 1944,1946-1997, 2009, undated
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Encampment for Citizenship Collection, 1939-1941, 1944,1946-1997, 2009, undated
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 391
5.78 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Special Collections and Archives in 2010 and 2011 by Margot Gibney, Pamela Barefoot, Marion Silverbear, and Nancy Marr.
Historical Information
The Encampment for Citizenship (EFC), a national youth program affiliated with the American Ethical Union, was founded in 1946, by Algernon D. Black, social activist and New York Society for Ethical Culture leader, and Alice K. (Nanny) Pollitzer, prominent civic leader and Ethical Culture Movement member. In response to the rise of fascism abroad and to the country's domestic problems of the day, it was their intention to create "community learning environments for youth which transcended racial, ethnic, class, religious and national boundaries," a vision inspired by their belief that "young people would grow as citizens and leaders if they lived and worked together in self-made democratic communities." From this experience, it was hoped that they would "develop a deeper knowledge of themselves and a vision of a more humane society."
The EFC's primary objective became "the creation of a responsible, informed and effective citizenship among American youth" capable of helping to solve society's most complex and intractable problems, and the organization aimed to foster youth leadership and civic involvement within a decidedly multicultural framework. Program participants were encouraged to examine current political, social, and economic issues through a curriculum designed to develop critical thinking and leadership skills. Over the years, the program came to include internship and community service projects, field trips, political activities, and community government participation. In addition, a wide variety of workshops, discussion groups, and lectures were held, in which the following types of subjects would be explored: social and economic justice, health and poverty, criminal justice, international relations, human rights, the environment, labor politics, education reform, racism and sexism, community and economic democracy, and youth empowerment.
Between the Encampment's inception in 1946 and dissolution in 1995, more than 7,000 young people from a diversity of racial, ethnic, religious, economic, and geographic backgrounds participated in EFC annual summer sessions, year-round leadership training programs, and various short-term projects. Some notable EFC alumni include: Gale Brewer, Ada Deer, Barney Frank, William Haddad, David Harris, Allard Lowenstein, Jean McGuire, Eleanor Holmes Norton, Charles Patterson, David Rothenberg, Hal Sieber, and Floyd "Red Crow" Westerman.
For several decades, the EFC enjoyed a national reputation. Prominent Encampment supporters included Eleanor Roosevelt, who served as Chairwoman of the EFC Board of Sponsors from 1946 to 1962, and Martin Luther King, Jr. In the 1950s, the organization was viewed by some with suspicion, including the American Legion, which accused the EFC of being "un-American" and "socialistic." Widespread support for the organization continued through the 1970s, but began to wane in the 1980s within the country's conservative political climate. By the early 1990s, the Encampment had lost most of its funding base, which ultimately led to its demise. In 2010, efforts by former EFC leaders and alumni were begun to revive the Encampment, and there continues to be growing interest and support for a revitalization of the organization.
Scope and Content
Special Collections and Archives began collecting records of the Encampment for Citizenship (EFC) in the spring of 2010, and it is expected that the burgeoning collection will become more comprehensive as the procurement of materials continues. As of February 2011, donations have been made by: Margot Gibney, former EFC National Executive Director; Marion Silverbear, former EFC Alumni Coordinator and Development Coordinator; Pamela Barefoot, a former EFC staff member; and Nancy Marr, an Encampment alumna. Dr. Edward H. Peeples, Emeritus Associate Professor of Preventive Medicine and Community Health at Virginia Commonwealth University, has been involved in coordinating donation efforts. Dr. Peeples' affiliation with the EFC began when he attended the 1957 Encampment, and he remained actively involved with the organization as a recruiter, site Director, guest speaker, and advisory committee member. There are additional records related to the EFC in the Edward H. Peeples, Jr. Papers, which are also located in Special Collections and Archives.
Materials in the collection include Encampment publications, program and recruitment brochures, student applications, fundraising and sponsorship materials, staff handbooks, student and staff evaluation questionnaires, student and staff workshop materials, photographs and slides. The collection also contains correspondence and memoranda of EFC staff and board members, letters and correspondence of students and alumni, alumni and staff directories, alumni newsletters and reunion materials, yearbooks, and newspaper and magazine articles. The bulk of the materials date primarily from 1946 to 1997, with concentrations in the collection's holdings dating from the late 1970s to the early 1980s, and from the late 1980s to the mid-1990s. Much of the collection's correspondence records are from these periods.
Arrangement
Materials in the collection are in alphabetical order within each container.
Contents List
- Donation from Margot Gibney n.d., 1947-1950, 1952-1953, 1957-1958, 1961, 1963-1970, 1972, 1974, 1977-1980, 1988-1994, 2009, undated (Box 1, 2(oversized), 3)
  - Summer encampment negatives undated (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Summer encampment slides 1977-1980, undated (Box-folder 1:2)
  - EFC artwork transparencies 1991 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - EFC brochure layout and logo roughs 1991 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - EFC brochure pages (layout roughs), summer program 1992 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - EFC event invitation, reply card and envelope layout roughs 1992 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - EFC fundraising event invitations, reply cards and envelopes (layout roughs) 1990 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - EFC summer program brochure layout roughs 1991-1994 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Encampment newsletter pages (layout roughs) 1990 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Encampment photograph 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Encampment photograph undated (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Encampment photograph undated (Box-folder 2:10)
  - "EYES in Review", January 1991-October 1992 issues undated (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Photograph of Eleanor Roosevelt for EFC brochure (layout rough) 1991-1992 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Photograph, Southern Appalachian Encampment, Lees Junior College, Jackson, Kentucky 1991 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Scrapbook of programs sponsored by EFC, EYES, New Bridges, YEP, and others 1991-1992 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - EFC brochure, newspaper clippings 1949, 1961, 1964 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - EFC poster 1993 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - EFC slideshow narratives and notes 1988-1991 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - EFC summer program application 1990 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - EFC summer program brochure layout roughs 1989 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Excerpts from EFC applications, layout roughs 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Film negatives 1993 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Information on Allard Lowenstein from book, "Never Stop Running" 2009 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Miscellaneous photographs and correspondence 1989-1994, undated (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Photographs 1993 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Photographs 1994 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Photographs, "Campers Gleening Lettuce with Ada Deer" 1991 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Photographs, EFC retreat February 5, 1994 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Photographs, EFC service projects 1991 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Photographs, "EFC/To do's" 1994 (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous undated (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous 1947-1948, 1950, 1952, 1967-1970, 1972, 1974, 1988, 1992, undated (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous 1950 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous 1953, 1957-1958, 1963, 1966, undated (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous 1958, 1961, 1965-1967, undated (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous 1961, 1966, 1978 (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous 1989, undated (Box-folder 3:22)
  - Photographs, negatives and contact sheets of banquet 1972 (Box-folder 3:23)
  - Photographs, summer program and fundraisers 1990 (Box-folder 3:24)
  - RYLC Retreat Goals and Draft Agenda 1993 (Box-folder 3:25)
- Donation from Pam Barefoot 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - EFC recruitment brochure 1974 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - EFC recruitment handbill 1974 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Letters by 1973 Denver EFC director Vincent Wright and Encampers to Colorado governor regarding their prison visit and prison reform 1973 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Newspaper article about picketing by UFW members and supporters, including 1973 Denver Encampers 1973 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Newspaper article by EFC staff member Pam Barefoot about the 1973 Denver EFC 1973 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Photograph, Denver EFC, campers and staff, including Pam Barefoot and director Vincent Wright 1973 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Photographs, Denver EFC, "Building Playground" 1973 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Photographs, Denver EFC, "Camping Trip" 1973 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Photographs, Denver EFC, "Neighborhood and School" 1973 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Photographs, Denver EFC, "Staff" 1973 (Box-folder 4:10)
- Donation from Marion Silverbear 1939-1941, 1944, 1946-1996, undated (Box 5, 6)
  - Analysis of Encampment Experience, Summer 1977, by Jon Kerner 1977 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Articles about Edward Peeples 1984, undated (Box-folder 5:2)
  - "The Balcony" undated (Box-folder 5:3)
  - The Center for Education in Democracy of the EFC Summer 1964 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - The Center for Education in Democracy of the EFC Summer 1965 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Chicago/Midwest Region Alumni Association Documents 1987, 1989, 1990, 1992-1993, undated (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Correspondence between Algernon Black and Winston Wright 1967-1969 (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Correspondence of Algernon Black regarding EFC dinners 1963-1964 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Correspondence of Armand Weiss, EFC alumnus 1950, 1952, 1954, 1974, undated (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Correspondence of Educational Program Committee Chairman Anna Lee Hopson 1973 (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Correspondence of EFC executive director Robert Lubetsky 1977-1978, 1981-1982, 1984, undated (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Correspondence of Honorary Chairman Algernon Black 1956, 1967, 1973, 1975, 1977-1984, 1986, undated (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Correspondence regarding EFC revival 1984, 1986 (Box-folder 5:13)
  - "The Dynamics of Attitudinal Change in a Citizenship Training Program", a proposal for research submitted to the EFC 1958 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - "The Echo", vol. 1, no. 1 August 2, 1957 (Box-folder 5:15)
  - Education Conference Weekend at Hudson Guild Farm 1989 (Box-folder 5:16)
  - Educational Program for 1946 Encampment 1946 (Box-folder 5:17)
  - EFC 50th Anniversary Celebration 1996 (Box-folder 5:18)
  - EFC administrative evaluations of Encampment programs 1973, 1978 (Box-folder 5:19)
  - EFC admissions and recruitment 1965, 1973, 1975-1977, 1979-1982, 1995-1996, undated (Box-folder 5:20)
  - EFC alumni activity updates undated (Box-folder 5:21)
  - EFC Alumni Directory Spring 1959 (Box-folder 5:22)
  - EFC alumni list 1946-1957, 1959-1964, 1966, 1969, undated (Box-folder 5:23)
  - EFC alumni newsletters 1954, 1966, 1970, 1973, undated (Box-folder 5:24)
  - EFC alumni responses to Algernon Black query 1960, undated (Box-folder 5:25)
  - EFC alumni stories, testimonials, news undated (Box-folder 5:26)
  - EFC annual budgets 1967-1968 (Box-folder 5:27)
  - EFC annual dinner, New York, NY, May 22, 1972 1971-1972 (Box-folder 5:28)
  - EFC Board correspondence 1972-1978, 1980-1981, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 5:29)
  - EFC Board members 1968-1978, 1981-1982, 1984, 1986, undated (Box-folder 5:30)
  - EFC Board of Directors meetings 1978, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 5:31)
  - EFC brochures / application forms and flyers 1950, 1954, 1957-1958, 1961-1964, 1968-1969, 1971, 1977, 1981, 1987-1988, 1990-1993, 1996, undated (Box-folder 5:32)
  - EFC by-laws 1965, 1986 (Box-folder 5:33)
  - EFC and Center for Education in Democracy newsletters 1964-1965 (Box-folder 5:34)
  - EFC Documentary Radio Script undated (Box-folder 5:35)
  - EFC Educational Policy / Program Committee meetings 1967, 1969, 1971-1975, 1978-1980, undated (Box-folder 5:36)
  - EFC evaluation questionnaire forms undated (Box-folder 5:37)
  - EFC Executive Committee 1978, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 5:38)
  - EFC Literary Magazine 1988-1990 (Box-folder 5:39)
  - EFC Log 1946 (Box-folder 5:40)
  - EFC Magazine 1987 (Box-folder 5:41)
  - EFC miscellaneous documents 1961, 1968, 1972, 1977-1978, 1987, 1989, 1993-1994, 1996, undated (Box-folder 5:42)
  - EFC production, "Mass Chant" undated (Box-folder 5:43)
  - EFC program 1950 (Box-folder 5:44)
  - EFC program 1966 (Box-folder 5:45)
  - EFC programs 1968 (Box-folder 5:46)
  - EFC programs 1991-1992 (Box-folder 5:47)
  - EFC publication, "The Citizen", v.1, no. 3 August 9. 1946 (Box-folder 5:48)
  - EFC publication, "Summer Projects" Winter 1967 (Box-folder 5:49)
  - EFC reunion brochures 1954, 1957 (Box-folder 5:50)
  - EFC song books 1950, undated (Box-folder 5:51)
  - EFC sponsorship 1952, 1965-1966, 1968, 1970, 1972, 1974, 1976-1980, 1982, undated (Box-folder 5:52)
  - EFC staff evaluations 1971, 1973, 1977, undated (Box-folder 5:53)
  - EFC staff handbook 1972 (Box-folder 5:54)
  - EFC staff meetings 1965 (Box-folder 5:55)
  - EFC staff training workshops 1981-1982, undated (Box-folder 5:56)
  - EFC student evaluations 1973, 1978, 1980 (Box-folder 5:57)
  - EFC training workshops 1992-1993 (Box-folder 5:58)
  - EFC writing workshop 1989 (Box-folder 5:59)
  - EFC year end reports 1981 (Box-folder 5:60)
  - EFC yearbook 1988 (Box-folder 5:61)
  - EFC yearbook 1989 (Box-folder 5:62)
  - EFC yearbook 1991 (Box-folder 5:63)
  - EFC yearbook 1992 (Box-folder 5:64)
  - EFC yearbook 1993 (Box-folder 5:65)
  - EFC yearbook 1996 (Box-folder 5:66)
  - EFC "Youth Creating a Future", conference and reunion 1993 (Box-folder 5:67)
  - "Encampment Bulletin", Reunion Issue 1958 (Box-folder 5:68)
  - Encampment directories, updated 1957 (Box-folder 5:69)
  - "Encampment Examiner", vol. 1 August 1, 1982 (Box-folder 5:70)
  - "Encampment Ink" Summer 1991 (Box-folder 5:71)
  - "Encampment News" 1987, 1989-1995 (Box-folder 5:72)
  - EYES (Empowered Youth Educating Society) documents 1991-1994 (Box-folder 5:73)
  - Last testaments of encampers, Summer program 1990 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Lists of EFC contributors, members, and staff 1967, 1969, undated (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Memoranda to EFC Education Committee and Board members 1977-1979, 1981, undated (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Memoranda to Encampment site directors from Paul Barker undated (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Metzger-Price Fund 1980, 1986 (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence 1950, 1966, 1974, 1980-1981, 1983, 1988, 1990, 1993, undated (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Miscellaneous documents describing EFC mission, history, values 1963-1964, 1978, 1987, 1993, undated (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Miscellaneous documents related to the death of Allard Lowenstein 1980, 1982 (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Newspaper and magazine articles 1947, 1956-1958, 1960, 1965, 1987-1988, 1990-1993, undated (Box-folder 6:9)
  - "The Peacepipe", v.1, nos. 1-3 July 11-27, 1950 (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Photo proof sheets, EFC Summer programs 1991, 1993 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Photocopied photographs 1982, 1988-1989, undated (Box-folder 6:12)
  - Photocopied photographs of Eleanor Roosevelt 1946 (Box-folder 6:13)
  - Photograph captions 1966, 1969, 1976 (Box-folder 6:14)
  - Photographs 1947, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 6:15)
  - Photographs 1990s, undated (Box-folder 6:16)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous undated (Box-folder 6:17)
  - Portrait photos undated (Box-folder 6:18)
  - Political Action Handbook 1950 (Box-folder 6:19)
  - Professional evaluations of EFC programs 1968, 1972, 1978, undated (Box-folder 6:20)
  - Regional Encampment Advisory Committee meeting notes undated (Box-folder 6:21)
  - Reports on EFC camper demographics undated (Box-folder 6:22)
  - Stone Soup for the World (book) permissions agreement undated (Box-folder 6:23)
  - Work camp and other program brochures (non-EFC) 1939-1941, 1944, undated (Box-folder 6:24)
  - Writings of Algernon Black 1983, undated (Box-folder 6:25)
- Donation from Marion Silverbear 1946-1959, 1964, 1968, 1970, 1980, 1984-1997, undated (Box 7)
  - Articles on and by Edward Peeples, EFC Alumnus, EFC Site Director, and Professor of Preventive Medicine at Virginia Commonwealth University 1989-1990 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Correspondence among EFC administrators and EFC Advisory Board member and Site Director Vincent Wright 1987-1993, undated (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Correspondence among EFC administrators and EFC Alumnus, Advisory Board member, and Regional Director Joe Turner 1988-1993, undated (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Correspondence among EFC staff and Congresswoman and Georgetown University Law School Professor Eleanor Holmes Norton 1986-1987, 1991, 1996 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Correspondence among EFC's Board Chair and Executive Director, and Mark Weiss, Principal of Bronx Regional High School 1988-1989, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Correspondence, interviews, obituaries of Aline (Honi) Pollitzer, Weiss, daughter of EFC co-founder Alice K. (Nanny) Pollitzer 1984, 1987, 1989, 1991, 1996, undated (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Correspondence, mainly concerning EFC Alumni, among EFC Administrators and Loreine Kendrick, secretary to Algernon Black 1986-1993 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Correspondence of Alexander Tureaud, EFC Board of Directors and National Advisory Board member 1988-1989, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 7:8)
  - Correspondence of, and articles about, Congressman and EFC alumnus Barney Frank 1987, 1989, 1995 (Box-folder 7:9)
  - Correspondence of, and newspaper article about, Simeon Golar, Chairman of EFC Board of Directors 1988-1990 (Box-folder 7:10)
  - Correspondence of and regarding Algernon Black, EFC co-founder 1964, 1968, 1994 (Box-folder 7:11)
  - Correspondence of Edward Peeples, EFC Alumnus, EFC Site Director, and Professor of Preventive Medicine at Virginia Commonwealth University 1984, 1986-1987, 1989, 1996 (Box-folder 7:12)
  - Correspondence of EFC Alumni Coordinator and Development Coordinator Marion Silverbear 1988-1996, undated (Box-folder 7:13)
  - Correspondence of EFC Executive Director Margot Gibney 1986-1997, undated (Box-folder 7:14)
  - Correspondence of METCO Executive Director and EFC Alumna Jean McGuire 1986-1987, 1990-1994, undated (Box-folder 7:15)
  - Correspondence, photographs, obituaries of EFC Alumnus and Board member Charles Patterson 1985, 1987-1995, undated (Box-folder 7:16)
  - Correspondence, press releases, reports related to Robert Burkhardt, Director of the San Francisco Conservation Corp 1988, 1990-1991, 1995, undated (Box-folder 7:17)
  - EFC 50th Anniversary correspondence 1996 (Box-folder 7:18)
  - EFC Alumni correspondence 1986, 1988-1996, undated (Box-folder 7:19)
  - EFC Alumni demographics 1946-1959, undated (Box-folder 7:20)
  - EFC Alumni rosters and groups 1954, 1970, 1988-1990, 1992, 1996, undated (Box-folder 7:21)
  - EFC Board of Directors lists and correspondence 1988-1990, undated (Box-folder 7:22)
  - EFC Encamper evaluation questionnaire 1980 (Box-folder 7:23)
  - EFC mass chant 1946 (Box-folder 7:24)
  - EFC reunion materials 1986, 1993, undated (Box-folder 7:25)
  - EFC student enrollment forms and information 1993 (Box-folder 7:26)
  - EFC student recruitment initiatives, including alumni and organization outreach and sponsorship 1986-1996, undated (Box-folder 7:27)
  - Lists of, and newspaper articles about, famous EFC Alumni 1990, 1992, undated (Box-folder 7:28)
  - Miscellaneous organization literature, and conference and workshop flyers 1995, 1997 (Box-folder 7:29)
  - National Network of Youth Leadership (NNYLA) meetings correspondence 1991 (Box-folder 7:30)
  - Paper and article by, and resume and curriculum vitae of, Offie C. Wortham, President of Information Technology Exchange 1980, 1984, 1988, undated (Box-folder 7:31)
  - Philadelphia Area Youth Leadership Development Project, a collaboration of the EFC and Fellowship Farm 1995-1996, undated (Box-folder 7:32)
  - Photographs of Eleanor Roosevelt, Algernon Black, Alice k. (Nanny) Pollitzer 1946, undated (Box-folder 7:33)
  - Sponsoring organization applications and forms for the EFC's Youth Leadership Development Project 1996 (Box-folder 7:34)
- Donation from Nancy Marr 1950 (Box 8)
  - EFC Yearbook 1950 (Box-folder 8:1)